The following content is
provided under a Creative Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue
to offer high quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional
materials from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT
OpenCourseWare at ocw .mit .edu.
Shall
we start?
Let me
just say, this is a great adventure for me.
I'm to be here all on my own teaching a course that
involves learning from data. So it's an exciting subject,
and a lot of linear algebra goes into it. So
it's sort of a second course in linear algebra.
So there is a stellar
site established,
and that will be the basic thing
that we use.
This is a public
site, math .mit .edu,
learning from data.
And
so a
book is coming pretty quickly as we speak,
or
after we speak.
And that site has the table of contents of the book, which
would give you an idea of what could be in the course.
And I printed out a copy for everybody just of that one
page. This is probably the final, first and last handout,
maybe,
with the
table of contents, which you'll see there.
And also, you'll see there the first two sections of the book,
which is what I'll talk about today and on a little bit into Friday.
So that's linear algebra, of course, because
the course sort of begins with linear algebra.
Actually, things that you would know from 1806, but
this is a way to say this is really important stuff.
So that's what I'll do today.
I'd like
to
do some start on the linear algebra today.
And here's
the great facts about the course. At least,
we knew there were. So we taught
it last year, several of us together.
And we knew there wouldn't be a final exam, but we imagined there might
be quizzes along the way. But then we couldn't think of anything to put on
the quizzes.
So we canceled those.
But
you do learn a lot, nevertheless. And so I
guess we based the grades on the homeworks.
So the homeworks will
be partly linear algebra questions
and partly
online,
like recognizing handwriting,
stitching images together,
many other
things. And I'll talk about those as we go.
Right. Good.
Yeah. So
that's the general picture.
And I'll
say more about it today.
And I could answer any question about
it. So we're getting videotaped.
So
if anybody's bashful,
sit at the far back.
But
it'll be fun.
Yeah. You may know the
videos for 1806.
So this
is like the next step, 1806 -5. It's pretty
exciting for me.
So
any question? Or shall I do a little math?
Why not?
And then I'll say a little
more about the course,
just so you have an idea of
what's ahead.
Yeah. And it looks like this room is exactly
the right size to me. So I'm pleased.
OK.
So what's the
deal in linear algebra?
Forgive me if I start with what I do the very first
day in 1806, which is multiply a matrix by a vector.
Oh, okay. When we did the lecture we took a
really great
3,
4, 12.
And I'll always call matrices A.
So first step is just A times x,
A times a vector.
So I multiply A by, let's say, x1, x2, x3.
And how do
I look at that answer?
So the choice is think of the
rows of the matrix or think of the columns.
And if you think of the rows, which is the
standard
way to multiply, you would take the dot
product. So the first way is dot product
of rho
dotted with x.
Right,
2x1 plus x2 plus 3x3. It
gives you the answer a component at a time.
That's the low level way.
The good way to see it is vector
wise.
See this as
x1 multiplies that first column,
x2 times the second column,
117,
and x3 times the third column.
3,
4, 12.
Good.
So it's a combination
of vectors.
And of course,
it produces a vector.
And here we have
a 3 by 3 matrix. And our vectors are in R3.
And most vectors
will be in R3 or RN for this course.
So that's the right answer. And of course,
the first component is 2x1 and 1x2 and 3x3.
The same 2, 1, 3, the same dot product comes out right. But
you see it like sort of all at once instead of piecemeal.
So that's part of
the course. I guess part of what I hope to
get across is
thinking of a matrix as a whole thing, not just a bunch of 9 or m times
n numbers, but thinking of it as a thing. A matrix multiplies a vector to
give another vector.
Yeah. So when I say Ax,
you immediately think that.
You immediately think, OK, Ax has a clear
meaning. It's a combination of the columns of A.
So
now let me take that next step.
And the next step is think about all combinations
of the columns of A. We take the matrix A.
And we take all x's.
And we imagine all the outputs.
And what I want to ask you is,
what
does that look like? If I just take one x,
one vector x, I get a vector output. It takes
a vector to a vector. But now I take all x's,
all of vectors x in 3D.
And I get all these answers.
And I think
of them all together.
And so I've got a bunch of
vectors, infinitely many vectors actually.
And the question is, if
I plot those infinitely many vectors, what
do I have?
And the beauty of linear algebra is that questions like
this, you can answer them. And you intuitively see it.
You certainly see it in 3D. And you kind of have the right idea in 10
dimensions, even though most of us don't see too well in 10D in R10. But here
we got three.
OK. So do
you see what I'm
saying? I'm taking all x's.
So all Ax
gives us a big bunch of vectors.
And each of these vectors
is called the column space of A.
It's a space, in other words.
That's the keyword there, the column space
of A.
And
I'll just write it
as C of A when I need
letters for it.
OK, so I'm going to ask
you, what does this column space look like?
And that depends on the matrix.
R3.
Sometimes it's a smaller
set in R3, a space.
Do you know what it is in this case? Do I get all of
3D out of these guys by choosing all x1 and x2 and x3?
It seemed like if
it was a random matrix,
the answer would be surely yes.
If a random 3 by 3 matrix is
going to,
its column space is going to be all of R3.
Its columns are going
to be independent.
Its rows are going to be independent. It's
going to be invertible.
It's going to be great. But
is this matrix, what's up with that matrix?
No, it's not.
So what do I get
instead of all of R3?
I
get a plane. Yeah, if you get that insight.
So
by taking
all x's, everybody's with me, all x's here.
So that means that
it fills in whatever.
And well, because it's linear algebra, it's
going to be likely
all of R3 or a plane
or even a line.
Let me just
bat over here for a moment.
Give me a matrix whose
column space would only be a line.
All ones.
OK,
wow, that's a, let me liven it up a little.
3, 3, 3,
8, 8, 8.
I think,
OK.
So I think that the combinations
of those columns are all on the same line.
That
says that the column space is just a line.
And I would say then that the matrix,
so column space of this A is a line.
Another way I could say
this is that the rank of the matrix
is 1.
The rank is sort of the dimension of the column space. Well, not sort of.
That's what it is. The rank is the dimension of the column space. Everybody
sees that you get a line? Because any
combination x1 of that plus x2 of that plus
x3 of that is
going to go in
along that line. Here's
the first column. Here's the second column.
They're all on a line.
Well, I'll
never get off that line.
If I allow all x's, I'll get the
whole line.
Now here, you said
not a line, right? What
was the column space for this guy?
Plane.
Now why isn't it all of R3?
What
do you see that's special there?
Because it is special.
That's
making the column
space sort of special,
a plane instead of
the whole thing. Yeah.
What's up
with these three columns?
The sum of the columns is the sum of these
two. The
third column
is the sum of these two.
So the first column is fine,
2, 3, 5.
Second column is
in a different direction.
And when I take combinations
of the first two columns, what will I get?
Sorry to keep asking you
questions, but that's,
anyway, that's what I always do.
So
the combinations of those first two columns
are
a plane,
because they're indifferent. Everybody kind of sees that picture. We've
got column 1 going that way and column 2 going that way. And then if I take
any multiple of column 1, I've got a whole line, any
multiple of column 2. And then when I put the two together,
it fills in the plane.
Yeah. Yeah.
Your intuition says that's right.
So this is a matrix of rank.
What's the rank of this matrix?
2.
Because it's got two independent columns, but the third column
is dependent. The third column is a combination of the others.
So matrices like this are really
the building
blocks of linear algebra.
They're the
building blocks of data science.
They're rank 1 matrices.
Let me show you a
special way to write those rank 1 matrices.
I think of this matrix
as the column vector 1, 1, 1 times the row
vector 1, 3, 8.
So it's a column times a row.
That's a rank 1 matrix.
Do you see that?
That's a true multiplication there. It looks a little
weird, but it's a 3 by 1 matrix times a 1 by 3 matrix.
These numbers have to
be the same. And then the output is 3 by 3.
And it's that.
And you see that it factors.
So I'm going
to move on to that idea.
The next idea
coming up will be that
we can see, well, that's coming, that we're
going to see matrices with two factors.
OK. Let me move to that, but back for this
original matrix.
OK.
So what's with this?
The column space is a plane.
So think about now the
key idea of independent columns.
How many columns have
I got here?
Two. Correct. Two. The third column, if I want to especially pick on that
one, so I'll often go left to right. So I'll say the first guy is good.
Second guy is good. The
third guy is not independent of the others.
So I
just have two independent columns.
And those two columns would be a basis for
the column space.
So that's the critical idea of linear algebra.
That's what you compute with. You find a basis.
And everything in
the column space is a combination of these,
including that.
That's already a combination of those. But everything
else in the column space is a combination of those two.
So they're a basis for it. OK.
So you have
the idea of A times x.
You have the idea
of column space of A, which allows all x's.
Then now we're moving
into the idea
of independent columns.
And the
number of independent columns is the rank.
So the rank,
shall I write that somewhere?
Maybe here, the
rank is the number of independent columns.
And right now, what do I mean by independent columns?
Well, let's just see what that means by using it.
Are
we
good? I know I'm reviewing here.
But allow me for this first
class and part of next time also to review. But you'll see
something new. In fact, why don't we see something new right away?
Let me
follow up on the idea
of independent columns.
OK.
We did write that the
most pointless problem
Here's Clean So
we can, see that it's the common approach.
natural way.
So I'm going to take a basis.
What's a basis?
A basis is
independent columns.
So all three together
would not be a basis.
But there have to be not just independent, but they have to
fill the space. Their combinations have to fill the space.
So 2, 3, 5, let's say
I want to create a basis.
I'll call the matrix C,
a basis for the column space. So here's a
natural way to do it. I look at the first column.
It's not zeros. If it
was all zeros,
I wouldn't want that in a basis.
But it's not.
So I put it in.
So that's the first vector in my
basis.
Then I go on
to the second column.
If that column was 4, 6, 10,
what would I do?
If that second column
was 4, 6, 10, would I put it in the basis?
No.
But 1, 1, 7 is OK, right? 1, 1, 7 is in a different
direction. It's not a combination of what we've already got.
So I say, OK,
that had
something new. Put it in.
Then I move
on to the third column.
Do I put that into a basis?
You know the answer by now, no.
Because I'm looking to see,
is it a combination of
these guys?
And it is.
It's one of that plus one of that. So it's
not independent. So I've
finished now.
I've got
a matrix C,
which was taken directly from A.
And I kept only independent columns. And I
worked from left to right.
And I
can see right away now that the rank is 2.
The column rank.
I should say the column rank.
The number of independent columns
is 2.
Good?
Now comes a key step.
I'm going to
produce a third matrix R,
which is going to tell me how to get these
columns from these columns.
And its shape is going to be, well,
its shape, I don't have any choice.
This is 3 by 2.
So R has to be 2 by something.
So
I'm like so.
by 3, because I want to come out this way.
2 by 3.
What am I going to do here?
I'm just going to put in the numbers R that
make this correct.
So this is a first
matrix factorization.
Well, it is a famous one, actually.
When we see it, we'll recognize what it is.
It's famous in teaching linear algebra, but
now actually
C times R, columns
times rows, has become very, very important
in large scale
numerical linear algebra.
So let's figure
out what goes into R.
So what's
going in? What am I thinking here?
I'm putting in R.
So every one of these columns is a
combination of these. That's the whole point.
So you have the numbers
that you need.
So what goes in the first column
of R?
What goes in
the first column of R?
So I want
to look what combination of that
column and that column
gives me this one?
1, 0. 1, 0.
Because
you remember how we multiply a matrix by a
vector?
When I multiply that matrix by that vector, I take
1 of this plus 0 of that. I see it vector -wise.
And of course, I get it right.
And what about the second column
of R?
So the second column should
be the combination that produces
the second
column of A correctly.
What will that be?
0, 1. Thanks.
And finally, the third column.
1, 1.
Yes, right.
Because 1 of this plus
1 of this produces the third column.
So all I did
was put in the right numbers there, really.
Right.
And
this is correct now. A
is C times R.
And so this is like
what
I've done here is like the first two pages
of section 1 .1 in these notes.
So 1 .1.
And actually, so I'll
tell you literally what happened
earlier this year.
I'd finished this.
I wrote this down
with a different example.
And then I realized something. That sitting
here in front of me was
the first
great theorem in linear algebra.
The fact that
the column rank equals
the row rank.
The fact that if I have a matrix
where that column
plus that column gives that one.
Oh, ooh.
So what am I going
to say here? I'm getting nervous about it.
I believe that a
combination of the rows
gives 0.
Do you believe that? I mean, you've got to believe it. This is like linear
algebra. The matrix is not invertible. It's square. But the columns are
dependent.
So the rows
have to be dependent.
And I don't exactly see.
There's some combination of
that row and that row that gives that one.
And of course, when I looked at the first
column, I thought, OK, it's going to be too easy.
One of that and one
of that gives that. But
then my eye went over to the second column. And I realized it's not easy
at all. So you're entitled to pull out your phone and figure this out.
But there is some damn combination
of those two rows. It gives the third row.
Otherwise,
like the course is over, we stop.
But maybe we're going
to find it somehow.
Yeah, yeah.
So this is the theorem.
So I have to
tell you, I
mean, I was like really pleased.
So the first two
pages got two more pages
to follow up on that idea. That here we were seeing something that I sort
of proved in 1806, but not in the first lecture, that's for sure. And not
maybe
so clearly. But now can I try to prove it?
So there
won't be a lot of proofs in this
class. But this is such an important fact.
A equals CR
is important factorization. And out of it,
we can connect them.
So what am I saying?
I am saying that all that the
row, so what's the row rank? Yeah, back up
here. What's the row rank?
What's the row space? So the row rank
is going to be the dimension of that space.
So I look
at my matrix A, what's the row space of A?
I'm going to look at its rows.
Now, maybe just so we don't
get whole new letters for the row space,
I'm,
for me, the row space
of A of a matrix.
So
first of all, tell me in words what it is.
What's the row space of
the matrix?
All combinations of
the rows.
All
combinations of the rows. That's the space.
So I would
take all combinations
of those rows.
To get combinations of the rows, I, well, two ways I can get combinations
of the rows. And the way I'll do it is I'll just transpose the matrix.
So those rows become columns. And then I'm
back to what
I did. So the row space of A is
the column space
of A transpose.
And this has the advantage
that we don't introduce a new letter.
So
it'll be the column space of
A transpose.
It's a totally different space.
And actually, I happen to take
a 3 by 3 example,
so that the column space is part
of R3.
And the row space is also part of R3, because
my matrix is 3 by 3. A better example,
and the whole point of
data, data doesn't come in square matrices.
Fortunately for us, data
very, very often comes in matrices.
But the two, the columns
might be sample,
might be patients. And
the rows might be diseases or something. I
mean, they're different spaces.
So matrices are not
likely to be square.
But anyway, we're good here.
OK.
So the row space.
Now can I come back
to the proof? Because
what I want to say is
that the proof of this
fundamental fact is
staring at us. But we
don't quite see it yet.
And I want to see it.
So I claim
that
these rows
are a basis
for the row space.
And we already
saw that these columns
are a basis
for the column space.
And 2 equals 2.
Two vectors here
were a basis for the column space. Now if I can see why this
shows me that these two vectors are a basis for the row space,
then my
example is right.
Both of these will
give 2. The column rank is 2, two columns.
The row rank is 2, two rows.
So
I have to explain why
I believe that these two
rows are a basis for the row space.
Right?
Are you with me? I have to prove, I have to
see why.
So
when I say basis, what do I have to check?
Basis is just the critical idea.
I have
to check that they're independent.
So I haven't got too many vectors. I haven't got any extra vectors
in there. And I also have to check that their combinations produce
all the rows.
Should I say that again? Because that's what I'm going to check. I'm going
to check that those guys are independent. Well, you can see that they're
independent.
And I'm going to check that their
combinations produce all three of these rows.
We didn't
create those numbers for this
purpose. But what I'm saying is they work.
So I
claim that this is a basis because
what combination of those
two rows would produce this first row?
Yeah,
let me just ask you that. What combination,
what numbers should I multiply these
two rows by to get the first row of A?
2 and 1.
And where do you find 2 and 1?
It's sitting there in C.
Will it work again?
Does 3 of this plus 1
of that, give 3, 1, 4?
Yes.
So far, so good.
Does 5 of this and 7 of that?
I'm multiplying.
I guess I'm doing matrix multiplication
a sort of backward way or a different way.
I'm taking combinations of the rows of the
second guy.
That's another way. The wonderful thing about matrix multiplication is
you can do it a lot of ways. It comes out the same every way. And each way
tells you something.
So 5 of that row plus
7 of that row, sure enough, is here.
Do you see that that
is not like accident?
The
proof is really to look
at this multiplication C times R two ways.
Look at it first as
combinations of columns
of C to give the columns.
Look at
it second as combinations of the rows of R,
and that produces the rows.
So that factorization,
A equals CR,
was
the key idea.
And actually,
this R that we've come up
with
has a name.
Anybody remember enough 1806?
Have you taken 1806?
No.
How many have?
Yes.
For a while, 1806
was taught in a very abstract way.
I said, what's going on? But anyway, so if
you took it that semester,
you maybe
never heard of the column space.
I'm not sure.
Or by a different name.
It has another name. What's its other name?
The column space of a matrix?
Range. I think it's the range.
Yeah, right.
Right. Yep. Yep. And of course,
all this is
fundamental in mathematics. So of
course,
everything here
has
different languages and different emphasis.
But you see what
the emphasis is here.
OK. So you see the proof that A equals CR.
R just reveals everything.
So it's a
first idea of a factorization of a matrix.
And
we've multiplied C times R. I could just say, because so that's really,
you've seen now the main point of section 1 .1 of the notes to come up with
that factorization and
that conclusion.
And you see why C has the same number of columns. The number of columns
of C equals the number of rows of R. And those are the column rank and the
row rank.
Yeah, it's just pretty neat.
And here
was the special case where those
column space, the column space is
all multiples of U. It's a line through U.
The row space is
all multiples of V. It's a line through V.
And that's the basic
building block. Yeah.
Can I just say another little word before I
push on beyond CR?
That this has become,
if you have a giant matrix,
like size 10 to the fifth,
you can't put that into fast memory. It's a
mess.
How do you deal with a matrix of size 10 to the
fifth when you cannot deal with all the entries?
It's not possible.
Well, you sample it.
So later in the course,
we'll be doing random sampling of a matrix.
So how could you
sample a matrix?
So you have a matrix. Of
course, you're not looking at it. But it's,
and you want to get
some typical columns.
OK, here's the natural idea.
You just look at A times x
when you take, let
x be a random vector.
Random vector.
Rand of,
so it's got m
rows and one
column. It's a vector.
And
what can I say about A x?
It's in the, what space
is it in?
Column space, thanks.
That was the first idea in this lecture.
A x is in the column space. So if you want a random vector in the column
space, I wouldn't suggest to just randomly pick one of the columns.
Better to
take a mixture of columns by taking
a random vector x and looking at A x.
And if you wanted 100
random vectors, you'd take 100 random x's.
And that would give you a pretty good idea in many cases of what the
column space looks like. That would be enough to work with often.
Yeah, OK.
Can
I just throw in another question?
So A x is in
the column space of A.
Let me
just ask you this question. Is A, B, C, x,
is that in the column
space of A?
Suppose I have matrices A, B, and
C and a vector x. And I take their product.
Does that
give me something in the column space of A?
Yes, good for you.
How do you know that?
A x is just easy.
Yeah, it's A times something.
Right.
Putting parentheses in the right
place is the key to linear algebra.
And there it is. OK.
A question just occurred to me. And I
thought, well, I wonder if you'd do it. OK.
So we have
still time to multiply matrices.
Oh, I was going
to say about C and R.
So these
are real columns from A.
But R is
the rows
are not taken directly from the rows of A.
Actually,
there's a name for this.
It's called
the row reduced echelon form of the matrix.
And it's a big goal in 1806.
It has the identity there. And then the other
columns tell you the right combinations.
Another
big factorization would be to take columns
from A. So this is another.
So I'll put maybe OR
A equal. And we won't
be doing this for a month.
We could start, take columns
of A and put them
into C if they were independent.
And suppose I took rows of A. Now I'm going to take literally rows of A and
put them into R. Well, so I call it R twiddle or something. Because it'll
be a different R.
I'm not going to use
those rows,
but I'm going to take two actual rows of A.
Then what?
So that's an important
factorization, but it's not correct.
If I took two other rows of R,
it wouldn't work.
So you have to put in the middle
some 2 by
2 matrix U that makes it correct.
You'll see in that section, 1 .1. And I got
excited and wrote a page about CUR.
So I'll just mention that.
So now I'm ready. Oh,
I wanted to say something about the course.
I get excited thinking
about math. But there is this course.
So what's up?
So there'll be linear
algebra problems.
But what makes
this course special is
the other homeworks,
which are online.
And you would use,
let's see, in principle, you could use any
of the languages,
MATLAB,
Python, which has become the biggest, most
used for deep learning,
or Julia,
which is the hot new language.
And
so last time,
last year,
the problems,
oh, so what happened last year?
Well,
everything
in this course is owed
to a professor who visited
from University of Michigan, Professor Rao,
Raj Rao,
who taught,
gave
most of the lectures a year ago,
brought these homework problems.
Online homework problems. So that people brought
laptops to class, and we did things in class.
And so he had and
has a very successful
course in EE in Michigan.
But he was a PhD from here, and he came back on a sabbatical, and
he created this, got us started. And we really owe a lot to him.
So Professor Edelman was involved with this
course. And you maybe know that he created Julia.
How many know what Julia is?
Oh, wonderful.
That will make his day.
He tells me every time I see him,
Julia's good. And I tell him, I believe it.
OK.
Anyway,
and it's become,
Professor Johnson
in 1806 has used Julia. And every semester,
Steven Johnson gives,
in the first week,
a tutorial
on Julia.
And so that's arranged,
and I promise to tell you when that is.
So I think if you
don't know anything about Julia, try to go.
It's in Stata.
It's on Friday
at 5, 5 to 7.
So Julia.
From
Professor Johnson.
So he's
done this multiple times. He's good at it.
So that's, I don't
think we know yet what,
I guess I'm hoping
that you'll have an option to use
any of the three languages.
But
the online thing that we give you was created
in Julia. So Professor Rao had to learn Julia.
Last spring. And the class did too. And there
was a certain amount of bitching about it.
But I think, with maybe one exception, who
still got an A, we,
everybody was kind of OK.
And was glad to learn Julia.
And Professor Rao now uses Julia entirely.
So he's creating
a new on -ramp with Julia.
MATLAB, by the way, has just issued an on -ramp to deep
learning that I'll tell you about. And probably get a MATLAB,
somebody from MathWorks
to
say something about it. Yeah, so
that's what's coming. We don't quite
know exactly how we'll organize those homeworks.
We'll just take the first one and see what happens.
So I'll certainly say more about homeworks
when the,
maybe even Friday.
But are
there other questions that I should answer?
Because some people will be thinking, OK, am I
going to do this? Or am I going to sit in 6036
or some other
course in deep learning?
Anything on your mind?
And you can email me.
So we will have a Stellar site. And you'll
see all the,
the TAs are still to be named. But the wonderful thing is that undergraduates
who took this course last year are volunteering to be graders for you
guys.
So they will know what
those online homeworks were about.
OK, so that's what's,
that's a sort of first
word
about what's coming and about the language.
Very important topic.
Multiplying A times B.
Oh, look, a clean board. So now I
want to multiply a matrix by a vector.
OK, everybody knows how
to do it.
You take a row of A. So you take
a row
of A.
And you take a column of B.
And you take the dot product.
So you get dot product.
Row dot column.
That's, again, low level.
Like, OK for beginners.
But
we want to see
that matrix multiplication AB in
a deeper way.
And the deeper way
is columns times rows.
Columns of A,
rows of B. Columns times rows.
Well, we had
a column times a row.
Right?
That was this rank one example.
We had a column times a row. And it produced
a matrix. And that's what it looked like.
And its rank was 1.
So those are what
we have.
So it's a combination of.
It's very like AX.
I'm really just extending the AX
idea to AB.
So
this is the old way.
The new way
is columns. So there's column K.
It will multiply.
Sure enough, it multiplies
row K.
Everybody sees that it will happen
that way. If you do it the old way, when
you do a dot product of something here, something here, you're doing these
multiplications. And when you hit column K here, you hit row K there.
So these are connected.
So
I get things like column K
of A
times row K
of B.
And I don't know what
notation to use. So I just wrote the words.
OK.
But now that's one piece
of the final answer AB.
That's a rank one piece.
That's like a building block.
So I add
from
K equal 1, column 1 times row 1,
column 1 of A times row
1 of B plus da da da plus column K plus.
And of course,
I stop
at column N
of A times row N of B.
So it's a sum of
outer products.
So
everybody sees this. Sum because
I have
column 1 times row 1,
column K times row K,
column N times row N.
And then I add those pieces.
It's just
the generalization of AX
to matrix
B there. So
it's a sum of column K,
row K of A,
row K of B.
And maybe we should
check that that gives us the right answer.
Or maybe I won't do that here.
But
all we're doing is the same multiplications
in a different order.
Actually, let's just quit. With one minute we can figure out how many
multiplications are there. How many multiplications to do a M by N matrix A
times a N by P matrix B? So that's A times
B. How many individual numbers,
because this would determine the
cost of it,
how many
numbers would we need?
Well,
suppose we do it the old way by
inner product,
row times column. So how many multiplications to do
a row times a column and get one entry in the answer?
N.
The
row has length N. The column has length N.
Multiplications.
So that's N.
And now how many of those do I have to do?
MP.
Because what's
the size of this answer?
The size of
this answer is M by P.
So if I do it in that old order,
like N multiplications
to do a dot product,
and I've got this many dot products in
the answer. So I've got M, N, P, multiply.
What guy?
MP.
And how many of those
rank ones do I have to do?
N.
You got it?
MP times N.
Now,
the other way was N times MP.
So it gives the same answer,
M, N, P, multiplication.
In fact, they're
exactly the same multiplications,
just a different
order. OK, we're at 1 .55.
Thanks for coming today.
I'll talk more about the
class and about linear algebra on Friday.
Thank you.